<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-02-02T18:48:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/atom.xml</id><title type="html">Faith of a Noob</title><subtitle>Training never ends.</subtitle><author><name>John Hansuld</name><email>jehansuld@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">100 Days of Code Challenge: Day Seven</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/100%20days%20of%20code/dayseven/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="100 Days of Code Challenge: Day Seven" /><published>2022-02-01T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-02-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/100%20days%20of%20code/dayseven</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/100%20days%20of%20code/dayseven/"><![CDATA[<p>Today I focused on getting my blog finished. It took a while but I needed a slow day. Work canceled so I had the day
    off and used it to relax and get back in the right headspace. <a href="/images/alphonse1.jpeg">Alphonse</a> was a
    huge fan of this idea and extremely supportive. I found a tech podcast a while back that I enjoy called <a
        href="https://learntocodewith.me/podcast/">Learn to Code with Me</a> by Laurence Bradford. I have been listening
    to it when I can't actually get to coding and on my rides to and from work. She interviews individuals in the tech
    field and pulls valuable advice from them. Listening to this podcast is when I put together how often people say
    they taught themselves to code and got a great job actually mean that they taught themselves enough code to do
    something and used their degree to get a job that helped them learn more and start a tech company.</p>

<p>So today my coding has been listening to this and finding new resources for freelancing. I do not think freelancing
    is a longterm solution for me, but I do believe that I can use it to force myself to learn more by doing it because
    it forces a deadline and puts my reputation and money on the line if I fail. As I am learning on my own, I do not
    really have the time crunch of deadlines except the ones I set myself and sometimes those can be hard to keep. My
    odd rotating hours and hectic life can be a real motivator to "do it tomorrow" instead of buckling down and getting
    something done.</p>

<p>Before I started the 100 Days of Code challenge, I was using <a href="https://theodinproject.com">The Odin
        Project</a> and Colt Steele's Udemy course, <a
        href="https://www.udemy.com/course/the-web-developer-bootcamp">The Web Developer Bootcamp 2022</a> ,as my
    learning completely. I still plan to use them but the blog was a necassary distraction for me. When I used these, I
    followed the Odin project until I got stuck, and then I would watch the videos on Udemy. So today I went back and
    did the projects and examples on Udemy as something easy that just helps enforce the knowledge I have gained.</p>

<h2>Key takeaways:</h2>

<ul>
    <li>Find a source of learning about the industry that interests you</li>
    <li>Find people that you admire in the field</li>
    <li>Do not ignore the fundamentals</li>
    <li>Alphonse is cute</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>John Hansuld</name><email>jehansuld@gmail.com</email></author><category term="100 days of code" /><category term="Journal" /><category term="Day 7" /><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="Encouragement" /><category term="Study Tips" /><category term="The Odin Project" /><category term="Udemy" /><category term="Learn to Code with Me" /><category term="Web Developer" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My journey to code]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Installing Jekyll</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/installingjekyll/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Installing Jekyll" /><published>2022-02-01T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-02-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/installingjekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/installingjekyll/"><![CDATA[<p>This is my guide on how to install Jekyll to use with <a href="/_posts/2022-01-31-githubpages.html">Github Pages</a>.
</p>

<p>I am going to go over how to do this in linux command line with links to the download files as well. All info can be
    found at <a href="https://jekyllrb.com">jekyllrb.com</a>. First we have to install some prerequsites.</p>

<h2>Install Ruby</h2>

<ol>
    <li>Download Ruby <a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/downloads/">here</a> or in linux command line: <p>
            <code>$ sudo apt-get install ruby-full build-essential zlib1g-dev</code>
        </p>
    </li>
    <li>Verify you have the latest version with: <p><code>$ ruby -v</code></p>
    </li>
</ol>

<h2>RubyGems</h2>

<p>If you installed Ruby with the command line instructions above, you may skip this step.</p>

<ol>
    <li>Download RubyGems <a href="https://rubygems.org/pages/download">here</a> </li>
</ol>

<h2>Linux install</h2>

<ol>
    <li>Create a folder to install your Gem files into. Never install it as a root user. Use: <p>
            <code>$ mkdir gems</code>
        </p>
    </li>
    <li>
        add your variables to the bashrc file by typing these commands. NOTE: $ indicates a new line so press enter for
        the previous command <p><code>$ echo '# Install Ruby Gems to ~/gems' >> ~/.bashrc</code></p>
        <p><code>$ echo 'export GEM_HOME="$HOME/gems"' >> ~/.bashrc</code></p>
        <p><code>$ echo 'export PATH="$HOME/gems/bin:$PATH"' >> ~/.bashrc</code></p>
        <p><code>$ source ~/.bashrc/code</p>
    </li>
    <li>The last step is to install Jekyll: <p><code>$ gem install jekyll bundler</code></p>
    </li>
</ol>

<h2>Windows install</h2>

<ol>
    <li>Press the windows key and type: <p><code>Command prompt</code></p>
    </li>
    <li>Select the Command Propt</li>
    <li>In Command Prompt type: <p><code>bash</code></p>
    </li>
    <li>Now we need to update our repository lists and packages. Type: <p><code>$ sudo apt-get update -y && sudo apt-get upgrade -y
    </code></p>
    </li>
    <li>Next we make sure RubyGems is up to date with: <p><code>$ gem update</code></p>
    </li>
    <li>Finally we install Jekyll: <p><code>$ gem install jekyll bundler</code></p>
    </li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>John Hansuld</name><email>jehansuld@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="Github" /><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="Hosting" /><category term="Guide" /><category term="Blogging" /><category term="Ruby" /><category term="RubyGems" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is my guide on how to install Jekyll to use with Github Pages.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">100 Days of Code Challenge: Day Six</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/100%20days%20of%20code/daysix/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="100 Days of Code Challenge: Day Six" /><published>2022-01-31T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-01-31T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/100%20days%20of%20code/daysix</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/100%20days%20of%20code/daysix/"><![CDATA[<p>This day I spent building the homepage css. It took me a while. I also did it 3 times and got frustrated. So I took a
    walk with <a href="/images/alphonse1.jpeg">Alphonse</a>. I decided that I am going to start off with a theme. I need
    to not focus on the details as much at the moment. The most important thing is to get the blog up and running and
    get back to focusing on studying. The experience of building my own blog as a project is good but I am stressing
    over the details currently. I will tinker with the site when I have spare time and need a break because I get stuck,
    but it will take time.</p>

<p>Using a theme for Jekyll came with it's own hurdles. I was able to get it installed, but was very quickly overwhelmed
    by trying to figure out how it formatted things. The theme that I chose was <a
        href="https://github.io/mmistakes/so-simple-theme">So Simple Theme</a> by <a
        href="https://twitter.com/mmistakes">Michael Rose</a>. My main issue was I ran into issues with the posts I had
    up. Everytime I cliked a post it took me to my latest post instead of the one that I clicked one. I struggled with
    this one for a while until I had to go to work.</p>

<p>When I got home I sat down and was very much exhausted from work. Going to work on the blog sounded awful and I had
    no desire to do anything. I decided to get a the new Pokemon game. <em>Pokemon Legends: Arceus</em>. So I booted up
    my Switch and began downloading the updates because I have not played it in a long time. prepped my lunch, and then
    started downloading the game. I promise my goal is not to tell you every little detail of my life, this is just to
    show how I went from not being willing to work on my project to telling myself that I can work on it for the time it
    would take to download the game.</p>

<p>So I sat down and started going through the code on the theme's github. I found the docs folder with a theme-setup.md
    file. This file is a step by step of customizing the site and following this and the files in the examples folder
    showed me where my mistake was. I had added the front matter to my site based on the read me file and they were not
    the same as those in the example files and the document files. Upon changing this everything just worked.</p>

<p>I have read that in coding, and in life, if you are struggling and cannot get focused then you need to give yourself
    a small victory or two will help you get back on track by increasing you general mood. Well it works. I spent the
    next three hours working on my site.</p>

<p>When I took my dog for a walk, it was a good distraction and help me get more energy. However, that is not always
    enough and when I finally solved a dificult problem, it made all the other problems just flow. I know it is not
    directly about coding but I think that the information I learned today with this will help me be a better programmer
    in the future. Most importantly though, it will make me a better student and help me stay on track.</p>

<h2>Key takeaways:</h2>

<ul>
    <li>Take breaks regularly</li>
    <li>Find something distracting and fun</li>
    <li>Have quick, easy projects lined up for a victory when you hit a wall</li>
    <li>Do not let perfecting the small details destract you from getting your project done</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>John Hansuld</name><email>jehansuld@gmail.com</email></author><category term="100 days of code" /><category term="Journal" /><category term="Day 6" /><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="Encouragement" /><category term="Study Tips" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My journey to code]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Github Pages</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/github/githubpages/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Github Pages" /><published>2022-01-31T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-01-31T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/github/githubpages</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/github/githubpages/"><![CDATA[<p>This guide will show you how to set up Github Pages for your own website or blog.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com">Github</a> is an extremely useful site for storing repositories of code. You can use it
    to showcase your project, or to collaborate on a project with others. Github Pages will create a repository that
    allows you to host it directly on the web. You can even attach a domain name of your choosing or you can use the one
    assigned which would be: <code>username.github.io</code> but this option will be completely free.</p>

<h2>Setting up Github Pages from scratch</h2>

<p>This option starts from scratch but is very simple. You will first need a Github account if you do not already have
    one. Keep in mind that your username will be attached to your site and will be public listed with all of your
    repositories. Choose something you will not regret. You can create an account at <a
        href="https://github.com">Github.com</a> by selecting the sign up button and following the prompts. You can do
    all of this with the free plan.</p>

<p>Next you will want to click the <code>Start a Project</code> button. When you name your project, make sure that you
    name it <code>USERNAME.github.io</code> replacing USERNAME with your actual username. This will tell Github to
    create a special webpage project that will push your files to that URL whenever there is a change. Make sure that
    you have selected the public option. You may also check the box to add a README file. This will not show anywhere on
    your webpage but it is a way to show those that come to your repository what your project is about.</p>

<p>From your repositories page, there will be a drop down menu named <code>Add file</code> in the top right. CLick then
    and select create new file. Name the file <code>index.html</code> then copy the following code into your
    file.</p>

<img src="/images/index-snippet.PNG" alt="">

<!-- This line is a seperator between the image and next paragraph -->
<p></p>

<p>Once you save this file you will click the settings tab above your repository. Then on the left side of the screen,
    under the Code and Automation section, click Pages. Under the Source section, verify that Branch: main is in the
    first drop-down and /root is in the second. Now above that should be a green box that says your site is published.
    Clicking the link will take you to your webpage.</p>

<p> <em><strong>CONGRATULATIONS!</strong></em> Your website is now up and running. Now you can use HTML and css to
    create a website. Or on the Pages settings screen, you can click the Theme button and
    choose a premade theme to make it easier for you.</p>]]></content><author><name>John Hansuld</name><email>jehansuld@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Github" /><category term="Github" /><category term="Hosting" /><category term="Guide" /><category term="Blogging" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This guide will show you how to set up Github Pages for your own website or blog.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Beginning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog%20info/beginning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Beginning" /><published>2022-01-30T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-01-30T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog%20info/beginning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog%20info/beginning/"><![CDATA[<h2>This is my First Post!</h2>

<p>I have begun the journey into tech, specifically into web development. Many have taken this journey and I have found
    numerous blogs, podcosts and videos that talk about these journeys. One thing that I noticed with these stories is
    that most of them had some sort of help. Many of them talk about having a degree. Some others talk about getting a
    job at a tech company or close to the IT
    department of a non-tech company. Another common one that I came across was that they quit their job to do a
    bootcamp or study at home or even get a degree in tech.</p>

<p>I do not have this advantage. I am 35 years old, and in the military as an aircraft mechanic. I have hit a point in
    which I am tired of working out in the weather. I am tired of the deployments and the long hours. I need a change. I
    could go to school for four years but from what I read, I can teach myself and get into a new job within a year. I
    figured I would document my journey to encourage others that can't just quit their job and feel like this path is
    something they cannot do.</p>

<h2>The Plan</h2>

<ul>
    <li>The plan is to make a blog post a day about my journey as a journal entry. This will also be part of my
        #100dayofcode journey.</li>
    <li>There will also be instructional posts for items that I come across with issues. Some of the instructional info
        I have found is either too advanced or was created years ago and is out of date.</li>
    <li>There will also be posts to review resources I have used and to recommend strategies and tips about how to use
        some of the resources.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Important Info</h2>

<p>This section is going to list the info for the beginning of my journey that might be different than others.</p>

<ol>
    <li>I am using a Lenovo Flex 14 that I wiped of windows and installed Ubuntu 20.04.3 that will be used solely for my
        coding journey.</li>
    <li>I have a desktop for everything else that I have been using to watch videos and find info while I code on the
        laptop.</li>
    <li>I work Monday-Friday, 9 hours a day. Currently working the night shift. This means that the military has me
        switch my hours randomly to fit their needs and do dayshift atleast once every two weeks.</li>
    <li>I am fulltime with the Air National Guard, this does mean that one weekend a month I am required to work during
        the dayshift. </li>
    <li>I have two boys that live two hours away. They are part of the reason for this journey because I want to move
        closer to them.</li>
    <li>I have a <a href="https://canineweekly.com/long-haired-german-shepherd/">Long Haired German Shepherd</a> named
        <a href="/images/alphonse1.jpeg">Alphonse</a>. He is full of energy and requires regular exercise. This will
        take away from coding time but will also
        make sure I stay active and take the all important breaks from long sessions.
    </li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>John Hansuld</name><email>jehansuld@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Blog Info" /><category term="Journal" /><category term="First Post" /><category term="Bio" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is my First Post!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">100 Days of Code Challenge - Day Five</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/100%20days%20of%20code/dayfive/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="100 Days of Code Challenge - Day Five" /><published>2022-01-30T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-01-30T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/100%20days%20of%20code/dayfive</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/100%20days%20of%20code/dayfive/"><![CDATA[<p>Today I got a good 4 hours in. Mostly researching. I learned how to install ruby and Jekyll on my laptop. Then I went
    through the process of setting up my blog with Jekyll. I still do not know all of it but I am learning. Jekyll
    allows for the use of <a href="https://www.markdownguide.org/">markdown</a> to be used in place of HTML for my posts
    but I have opted out of that
    and will continue using HTML. I personally see markdown as more useful for someone that wants just a quick blog or
    is not very technical. This blog is suppose to be a learning tool for me to improve my HTML, CSS, and Javascript
    skills.</p>

<p>I have a long way to go on the site, tomorrow I will focus on setting up the CSS side of things. I will also set up
    navigation to be better in the site by adding a category link and allowing sorting by date or by tag. I may make a
    todo list on the homepage to help keep me accountable.</p>

<p>Current list:
<ul>
    <li>CSS
        <ul>
            <li>blog cards on homepage</li>
            <li>set up blog pages</li>
            <li>set up homepage</li>
            <li>decide on logo, and create a permanent one(possible with SVG</li>
            <li>decide and implement color scheme</li>
            <li>homepage image or solid color</li>
        </ul>
    </li>
    <li>blog post
        <ul>
            <li>Linux install and setup</li>
            <li>Github Pages</li>
            <li>Jekyll install</li>
            <li>Jekyll guide</li>
        </ul>
    </li>
    <li>fill in About page</li>
    <li>add post page that can be sorted</li>
    <li>add a contact page</li>
    <li>add date to post with author name incase of guest post</li>
</ul>
</p>]]></content><author><name>John Hansuld</name><email>jehansuld@gmail.com</email></author><category term="100 days of code" /><category term="Journal" /><category term="Day 5" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My journey to code]]></summary></entry></feed>